Guide to the Isaac Ingalls Stevens Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Isaac Ingalls Stevens papers
1848-1859
WA MSS 442-445
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes) + 1 broadside folder.
The Stevens papers contain correspondence, reports, memoranda, and maps documenting the 1856 declaration of martial law in Washington Territory and Indian hostilities, relations with the Hudson's Bay Company and the Puget Sound Agricultural Company, and political events during Steven's administration (WA MSS 442-444). In 1857, Stevens prepared a map of the Washington and Nebraska territories for his report on the railroad survey with information on various Indian tribes, reservations, settlements, and military posts (WA MSS 445).
Stevens, Isaac Ingalls, 1818-1862
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
From the Winlock W. Miller Collection.
Arrangement
The collection consists of four groups previously cataloged separately as WA MSS 442, WA MSS 443, WA MSS 444, and WA MSS 445, and is organized into four series reflecting this previous arrangement.
Biographical / Historical
General Isaac Ingalls Stevens graduated from West Point and served in the Engineer Corps of the Army until 1853. He resigned to become governor of Washington Territory and also served as superintendent of Indian affairs until 1857. Stevens was appointed director of the survey of a northern route for a Pacific railroad.
Scope and Contents
The Stevens papers contain correspondence, reports, memoranda, and maps documenting the 1856 declaration of martial law in Washington Territory and Indian hostilities, relations with the Hudson's Bay Company and the Puget Sound Agricultural Company, and political events during Steven's administration. In 1857, Stevens prepared a map of the Washington and Nebraska territories for his report on the railroad survey with information on various Indian tribes, reservations, settlements, and military posts.
The Isaac Ingalls Stevens Papers have been organized in four series. The first series (WA MSS 442) consists of correspondence and other papers relating to Governor Stevens' proclamation of martial law in Washington Territory. The letters from Stevens and Adjutant General James Tilton found in this section of the collection are the file copies in the writers' hands or are signed by them. (For additional material, see the Elwood Evans Papers [WA MSS 187], as well as WA MSS 509, a "Proclamation ending the Indian War of 1856 and repealing the rule of martial law in Washington Territory," May 24, 1856.) Also found in the first section of the papers is a document entitled "Proceedings of a General Court Martial or Military Commission convened at Camp Montgomery by virtue of an order from Isaac I. Stevens, Governor of the Territory of Washington, and Commander-in-Chief of the Volunteer Forces thereof," May 20-29, 1856. The document is a manuscript in the handwriting of Quincy A. Brooks, recorder. The military commission consisted of Lieutenant Colonel J. S. Hurd, Major H. J. G. Maxon, Captain C. W. Swindal, Captain W. W. DeLacy, Lieutenant A. Shepherd, Lieutenant S. B. Curtis, supernumerary, and Victor Monroe, Judge Advocate. The proceedings are signed at the end by the members of the court, and approved, May 29, 1856, by Governor Stevens. There are fifty-seven letters and papers (144 pp.) in the first section.
The second series of the collection (WA MSS 443) consists of correspondence of Isaac I. Stevens, Governor of Washington Territory, during the years 1848 to 1857. There are 206 letters and papers (541 pp.) in this section of the collection. The correspondence deals chiefly with the Indian hostilities of 1856 and relations with the U.S. Army. However, the political affairs of the Territory under Governor Stevens, the relations with the Hudson's Bay Company and Puget Sound Agricultural Company, Mullan's explorations in 1853-54, the murder of White and Northcraft, and the trial of Leschi are also matters dealt with in the correspondence. The majority of the letters to Stevens are the originals, while those from Stevens are in most cases copies or drafts preserved by the writer for his files.
The third series of the Isaac Ingalls Stevens Papers (WA MSS 444) consists of a letter (a single page) written by the Governor to M[?] F. Schmidt on March 18, 1859. The letter contains instructions as to the chapter headings in the "Geographical Memoir," which is part of Stevens' Narrative and Final Report of Explorations for a Pacific Railroad, Washington, 1860 (U.S. War Dept. Reports of Explorations and Surveys, 1860, Vols. XII-XIII).
The fourth series of the Isaac Ingalls Stevens Papers (WA MSS 445) consists of a map which is mounted on linen and folded. The map is entitled "Prepared in the Office of Explorations & Surveys, War Department, from a Map of the Indian Nations and Tribes of the Territorys of Washington and Nebraska west of the mouth of the Yellowstone. Made under the direction of Isaac I. Stevens, Gov. of Wash. Terrt. & Supt. of Ind. Affairs" [April, 1857]. The map consists of the engraved map of the region from the Rocky Mountains to Puget Sound, prepared by Governor Stevens for his report on the survey for a Pacific railroad, with information added in manuscript about the Indian tribes and reservations, settlements, and military posts. There is a manuscript extension east of the Rocky Mountains to the Yellowstone River to show the more eastern tribes, and, inserted in the lower left corner in place of the original caption and part of Oregon, two tabular statements of the Indians west and east of the Cascades, showing "tribes, population, parties to the several treaties, reservations provided in the treaties, and temporary encampments," as well as "Notes of the Indians of the Territory of Nebraska between the Rocky Mountains and the mouth of the Yellowstone."
A month before Governor Stevens was relieved as superintendent of Indian affairs by Colonel James W. Nesmith, he sent a letter and map of the Indian nations and tribes of the Territory of Washington and of the Territory of Nebraska, with tabular statements and notes, to George W. Manypenny, Commissioner of Indian Affairs, April 30, 1857. The region from the Cascades to Fort Benton has been printed on a reduced scale, with much less detail, in Hazard Stevens, Life of Isaac Ingalls Stevens, 1900, I, facing p. 16, and the "Tabular Statements" and "Notes" appear as the Appendix to Vol. I, pp. 503-505, from the original on file in the Indian Bureau. The Miller map is a copy made for the Secretary of War.
Indians of North America -- Idaho; Indians of North America -- Northwest, Pacific; Indians of North America -- Washington (State); Pacific Coast Indians, Wars with, 1847-1865; Railroads -- Washington (State) -- History; Rogue River Indian War, 1855-1856; Salish Indians; Yakama Indians -- Wars, 1855-1859; Washington Territory -- Politics and government; Maps -- United States; Politicians -- Washington (State); Soldiers -- Washington (State); Casey, Silas, 1807-1882; Chenoweth, Francis A., 1819-1899; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889; De Lacy, W. W. (Walter Washington), 1819-1892; Douglas, James, 1803-1877; Evans, Elwood, 1828-1898; Gibbs, George, 1815-1873; Miller, William Winlock, 1822-1876; Mullan, John, 1830-1909; Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869; Shaw, B. F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1829 or 1830-1908; Steptoe, Edward Jenner, 1815-1865; Stevens, Isaac Ingalls, 1818-1862; Wool, John Ellis, 1784-1869; Wren, Charles; Wright, George, 1803-1865; Hudson's Bay Company; Puget Sound Agricultural Company; United States. Army. Washington Territory Volunteer Regiment, 2nd
- Papers relating to martial law in the Washington Territory (WA MSS 442), 1856; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The first series (WA MSS 442) consists of correspondence and other papers relating to Governor Stevens' proclamation of martial law in Washington Territory. The letters from Stevens and Adjutant General James Tilton found in this section of the collection are the file copies in the writers' hands or are signed by them. (For additional material, see the Elwood Evans Papers [WA MSS 187], as well as WA MSS 509, a "Proclamation ending the Indian War of 1856 and repealing the rule of martial law in Washington Territory," May 24, 1856.) Also found in the first section of the papers is a document entitled "Proceedings of a General Court Martial or Military Commission convened at Camp Montgomery by virtue of an order from Isaac I. Stevens, Governor of the Territory of Washington, and Commander-in-Chief of the Volunteer Forces thereof," May 20-29, 1856. The document is a manuscript in the handwriting of Quincy A. Brooks, recorder. The military commission consisted of Lieutenant Colonel J. S. Hurd, Major H. J. G. Maxon, Captain C. W. Swindal, Captain W. W. DeLacy, Lieutenant A. Shepherd, Lieutenant S. B. Curtis, supernumerary, and Victor Monroe, Judge Advocate. The proceedings are signed at the end by the members of the court, and approved, May 29, 1856, by Governor Stevens. There are fifty-seven letters and papers (144 pp.) in the first section.
  - STEVENS, ISAAC INGALLS
    - Three letters to Colonel Casey. Mar 31-Apr 7, 1856. 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Hon. F. A. Chenoweth. May 28, 1856. 2 p. Letter to Elwood Evans. Jun 3, 1856. 1 p. Letter to Lieutenant Colonel Lander. May 4, 1856. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Hon. Victor Monroe. May 28, 1856. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Four letters to Lieutenant Colonel Shaw. May 4-22, 1856. Signed by Stevens. 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Copies of two letters to the President of the United States [Franklin Pierce]. May 23, Aug 18, 1856. 9 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter to William F. Tolmie. Mar 8, 1856. 1 p. Copy of a few lines of Governor Stevens' answer to alleged cause of complaint, in the case of the U.S. vs. Isaac I. Stevens [Jul? 1856]. In the handwriting of Judge Strong. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BROOKS, QUINCY ADAMS
    - Letter to Governor Stevens. May 27, 1856. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CASEY, SILAS
    - Two letters to Stevens. Mar 31, Apr 3, 1856. 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CHENOWETH, FRANCIS A.
    - Two letters to Stevens. May 29, Nov 15, 1856. 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letter to Elwood Evans. May 30, 1856. 2 p. Two letters to Judge Lander. Apr 30 [copy in handwriting of W. W. Miller], May 29, 1856. 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft of the appointment of Elwood Evans to prosecute Charles Wren and others. May 29, 1856, in Judge Chenoweth's hand, and, on the same page, a copy of Elwood Evans' letter to Stevens notifying him of the fact, May 30, 1856. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft of a letter to Messrs. Ed[ito]rs [1856]. In Judge Chenoweth's hand. 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - EVANS, ELWOOD
    - Draft of a letter to the Hon. William Bigler. May 19, 1856. 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Two letters to George Gibbs, about the posting of the proclamation abrogating martial law. May 26, 1856. 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GIBBS, GEORGE
    - Letter to Evans. Monday 12 [May 1856]. 2 p. Drafts of three letters from Gibbs and Goldsborough to the Secretary of State, William L. Marcy. May [11]-Jun [6] 1856. 22 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Draft of his opinion on martial law. Undated. 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Drafts of two papers on martial law in Washington Territory, undated, the second written in answer to an article in a newspaper, probably the Pioneer and Democrat. 10 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Draft of a letter to the editor of the Oregonian on martial law in Washington Territory. Unsigned. 8 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - KENDALL, BEZALEEL FREEMAN
    - Letter to George Gibbs. May 10, 1856. 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - LANDER, EDWARD
    - Two letters to Stevens. May 4, 5, 1856, with a draft of the latter. 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Draft of a writ of habeas corpus and a writ of attachment, Charles Wren, et al. [vs. I. I. Stevens]. May 15, 1856, Edward Lander, To the clerk of the Thurston U.S. District Court, Wm. W. Miller. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - MARCY, WILLIAM LEARNED, Secretary of State
    - Letter to Stevens. Sep 12, 1856. Signature only. 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [MILLER, WILLIAM WINLOCK]
    - Summary in the handwriting of William W. Miller of the action taken against Governor Stevens. [n.d.] 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - MONROE, VICTOR, Judge Advocate
    - Letter to Colonel B. F. Shaw. May 2 [i.e., 22], 1856. Signature only. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter to Stevens. May 27, 1856, written by Quincy A. Brooks and signed also by Judge Monroe. 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - SHAW, BENJAMIN F.
    - Letter to Stevens. May 5, 1856. 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - TILTON, JAMES, Adjutant General, W.T.V.
    - Letter to the Commanding Officer at Fort Steilacoom, W.T. [Lt. Col. Casey]. Apr 2, 1856. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Copy of letter to President Pierce. Aug 18, 1856. 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Stevens. Aug 18, 1856. 3 p. Charges and specification of charges against Charles Wren. Certified copy signed by J. M. Bachelder, J.P. [1856.] 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - WASHINGTON TERRITORY. GOVERNOR (Isaac I. Stevens)
    - Draft of the proclamation of martial law in Pierce County, W. T. [Apr 3, 1856]. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Proclamation of martial law in Thurston County, May 13, 1856. Signed by Isaac I. Stevens. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Copy of the proclamation abrogating martial law in Pierce and Thurston Counties, May 24, 1856, with a deposition regarding the proclamation, signed by Simpson P. Moses, May 26, 1856. 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Draft of a respite issued by Governor Stevens to himself as defendant against the charge of con- tempt of court, in the handwriting of Judge Strong [Jul 10, 1856]. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - WASHINGTON TERRITORY. MILITARY COMMISSION.
    - Memorandum of the charges against the defendants, in the court martial [Lyon A. Smith, Charles Wren, and John McLeod], in the handwriting of Q. A. Brooks. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Proceedings of a General Court Martial or Military Commission convened at Camp Montgomery by virtue of an order from Isaac I. Stevens, Governor of the Territory of Washington, and Commander-in-Chief of the Volunteer Forces thereof," May 20-29, 1856. 16 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Governor Stevens' correspondence, 1848-1857. (WA MSS 443)
  General
  206 letters and papers. 541 p. Map. 18.5-37 cm.
  The second series of the collection (WA MSS 443) consists of correspondence of Isaac I. Stevens, Governor of Washington Territory, during the years 1848 to 1857. There are 206 letters and papers (541 pp.) in this section of the collection. The correspondence deals chiefly with the Indian hostilities of 1856 and relations with the U.S. Army. However, the political affairs of the Territory under Governor Stevens, the relations with the Hudson's Bay Company and Puget Sound Agricultural Company, Mullan's explorations in 1853-54, the murder of White and Northcraft, and the trial of Leschi are also matters dealt with in the correspondence. The majority of the letters to Stevens are the originals, while those from Stevens are in most cases copies or drafts preserved by the writer for his files.
  - STEVENS, ISAAC INGALLS
    - Correspondence with Colonel Silas Casey, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      Copies of 37 letters to Colonel Silas Casey. Feb 2-Dec 1, 1856. 77 p.; 22 letters from Casey to Stevens, Jan 31-Nov 12, 1856. 34 p. Casey's letter to Stevens, Apr 28, encloses a copy of a letter from Gibbs to Casey, Apr 20, 1856; and that of Nov 12 encloses a letter from Lieutenant D. B. McKibben to Lieutenant John Nugen, Nov 8, 1856.
    - Copy of letter to Colonel Sam Cooper. Feb 16, 1855. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Drafts and copies of 16 letters to Jefferson Davis, Secretary of War. Feb 19-Dec 6, 1856. 78 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with Sir James Douglas, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Copies of three letters to Sir James Douglas. Feb 17-Mar 8, 1856. 3 p.; Five letters from Douglas to Stevens. Jan 22, 1855- Mar 14, 1856. Signatures only. 13 p.
    - Three letters to George Gibbs. Aug 30, 1855- Feb 6, 1856. 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Captain Thomas Jordan, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Copies of two letters to Captain Thomas Jordan. Aug 3, Dec 4, 1856. 3 p.; Three letters from Jordan to Stevens. Jun 24-Oct 4, 1856. 5 p. Letters of Sep 4 and Oct 4 have signature only in Jordan's hand.
    - Copy of letter to Major Lugenbeel. Aug 3, 1856. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letter to G. N. McConaha. Mar 9, 1854. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Endorsed: "Received Mar 9, 1854 and referred to Committee on Roads and Highways. Elwood Evans, Chf. Clerk."
    - Copy of letter to O. B. McFadden. Feb 16, 1855. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letter to Captain M. Malony. Mar 16, 1857. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Two letters to C. H. Mason. Jan 29, Nov 14, 1856. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Hon. D. J. Pearce, enclosing some observations on the Military Academy at West Point, Jun 5, 1848; and a letter to Pearce from William H. C. Bartlett commenting on Stevens' observations. 10 p. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Copies of four letters to the President of the United States [Franklin Pierce]. Jan 29, Jul 12, 1856. 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence with Captain David Allen Russell, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Copies of two letters to Captain David Allen Russell. Aug 31, Sep 4, 1856. 2 p. Letter from Russell to Stevens. Sep 2, 1856. 3 p.
    - Correspondence with Lieutenant Colonel Benjamin F. Shaw, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Copies of two letters to Lieutenant Colonel Benjamin F. Shaw. May 21, Nov 5, 1856. 3 p.; Letter from Shaw to Stevens. Jan 17, 1856. 3 p.
    - Copy of letter to J. S. Smith. Jan 23, 1857. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence with Lieutenant Colonel Edward Jenner Steptoe (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Copies of five letters to Lieutenant Colonel Edward Jenner Steptoe. Aug 25-Nov 22, 1856. 9 p.; Seven letters from Steptoe to Stevens. Aug 28-Nov 2, 1856. 9 p.
    - Copy of letter to James C. Strong. Feb 16, 1855. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence with Dr. William Fraser Tolmie, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Copies of two letters to Dr. William Fraser Tolmie. Mar 26, May 15, 1856. 2 p.; Four letters from Tolmie to Stevens. Dec 27, 1853- May 22, 1856. 11 p.
    - Copy of letter to R. M. Walker. May 4, 1855. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Copy of letter to James G. Wood. Feb 22, 1855. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 22a)
    - Correspondence with General John Ellis Wool, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Drafts or copies of five letters to General John Ellis Wool. May 22, 1855-May 12, 1856. 32 p.; Five letters from Wool to Stevens. Feb 19, 1855- Feb 12, 1856. 13 p.
    - Correspondence with Colonel George Wright, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Drafts or copies of 13 letters to Colonel George Wright, Jan 30-Nov 22, 1856. 26 p.
      Six letters from Wright to Stevens. Feb 3-Oct 4, 1856. 13 p.
  - ALLEN, EDWARD JAY.
    - Letter to Stevens. Jan 29, 1856. 2 p. One picture of Kate Stevens (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - BACHE, ALEXANDER DALLAS.
    - Circular letter to Stevens, signed by A. D. Bache. Sep 26, 1856. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - CASEY, SILAS.
    - Two letters to Adjutant General Tilton, Feb 19, Mar 12, 1856. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - CLARK, FRANK.
    - Letter to an unnamed correspondent. Jun 4, 1856. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - DELACY, WALTER WASHINGTON.
    - "Itinerary of the march of the Right Wing of the Second Regiment of the W.T. Vols. under command of Lieutenant Colonel Shaw, from Montgomery's to Grande Ronde," Jun 12-Aug 29, 1856. To Governor I. I. Stevens. 49 p. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Map, "Plan of the battle of Grande Ronde fought Jul 17, 1856." 18.5 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - DOTY, JAMES.
    - Letter to Stevens, with information on the crossings of the Snake River, etc. Dec 21, 1855. 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Itineraries of routes from 'Whitman's Station' in the Walla Walla Valley to 'Craig's,' in the Nez Perce country, the Coeur d'Alene Mission and Spokane Prairie at Antoine Plantes." 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - DOYLE, REUBEN L.
    - Forwarding to Stevens a resolution of the House of Representatives requesting information about the survey of Grays Harbor. Jan 23, 1857. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - FITZHUGH, EDMUND C.
    - Three letters to Stevens. Dec 23, 1854-Mar 27, 1855. 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - HALLER, GRANVILLE OWEN.
    - Letter to Stevens. Apr 20, with postscripts, May 3, 5, 1857, enclosing copies of extracts from letters to Captain Maloney, Apr 5, Major Mackall, Apr 7, and Governor James Douglas, Apr 15, 1857. 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - MCCURDY, SAMUEL.
    - Two letters to Stevens. Apr 25, 1855, Dec 16, 1856. 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - MARCY, WILLIAM LEARNED.
    - Letter of instructions to Stevens. Jun 3, 1853. Signature only. 7 p. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - MULLAN, JOHN.
    - "Copy of reports and communications on affairs of Blackfeet & Selish Indians, and explorations from Nov. 1853 to Jan. 1854, from Lieutenant Mullan, U.S.A. to Governor Stevens," Nov 18, 1853- Jan 25, 1854. 26 p. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - NUGEN, JOHN.
    - Letter to James Tilton. Mar 3, 1856. Signature only. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letter to Lieutenant Colonel Shaw. Jun 1, 1856. Copy. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letter to Stevens. Dec 3, 1856. Signature and postscript in his hand. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - OGDEN, PETER SKENE.
    - Letter to Stevens. Jan 16, 1854. Signed also by Dugald Mactavish. 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - PACKARD, J. A.
    - Letter to Stevens. Oct 20 [1856]. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - PIERCE COUNTY, W. T. VIGILANCE COMMITTEE.
    - Draft of compact, Jun 1, 1856. Unsigned. 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - RICARD, PASCAL.
    - Letter to Stevens. Jan 29, 1856. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - RUSSELL, CHARLES J. W.
    - Letter to Stevens on the fisheries of the coast. Feb 6, 1856. 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - SIMPSON, SIR GEORGE.
    - Letter to Stevens. regarding the rights of the Hudson's Bay Company and the Puget Sound Agri- cultural Company. Mar 22, 1854. 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - SWARTWOUT, SAMUEL.
    - Letter to Stevens containing his report of the attack on the northern Indians near Port Gamble. Nov 23, 1856. 9 p. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - TILTON, JAMES.
    - Four letters to Colonel Casey. Jan 31-Mar 15, 1856. 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - WASHINGTON TERRITORY. GOVERNOR (I. I. Stevens).
    - Seven certificates of election to the first Legislative Council of the Territory. Executive Office, Olympia, Feb 25, 1854, signed by Isaac I. Stevens, Governor, and issued to Lafay- ette Balch, Daniel R. Bigelow, D. F. Bradford, Seth Catlin, Henry Miles, William H. Tappan, and B. F. Yantis. 7 p. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - A proclamation organizing the Territorial Government of Washington Territory. Nov 28, 1853, with additional proclamations dated Dec 1 and 3, 1853. Signed by Isaac I. Stevens, Governor, and C. H. Mason, Secretary. 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - WRIGHT, GEORGE.
    - Copy of letter to Colonel Shaw. Feb 21, 1856, with note to Governor Stevens added by Lieutenant Brackett, Q.M. Clerk. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Copy of letter to Colonel Shaw. May 27, 1856. 1 p. Copy of letter to J. F. Noble. Jul 15, 1856. 2 p. Copy of letter to Lieutenant Colonel T. Morris. Jul 26, 1856. 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Isaac Ingalls Stevens Letter to M.[?] F. Schmidt. (WA MSS 444), 1859 March 18; 1